Chapter One. The American Sound. Deepen your voice. Project it out. Let's start at
the beginning. As the philosophers say, start with yourself and define your terms.
What are the parts of your mouth? How do they interact? What's a consonant? What's
a vowel? Let's take a tour of the mouth, starting with the most basic sound.
Exercise 1-1. The starting point. Mmm. Let's start with the mmm sound. It's super
easy to do. All you do is put your lips together and hum. You'll notice a couple
of things here. Your lips are touching, the air is coming out through your nose,
in a continuous stream. Put your hand on your throat and say mmm and observe that
you can feel a vibration in your fingertips. This means that the M sound is
spoken and not whispered, mmm. This exercise tells you four important things
about the consonant M. One, point of contact, lips. Two, where the air comes
out of your mouth, nose. Three, how the air comes out, glide. Four, if the sound
is spoken or whispered, spoken.